<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learning | Maria Monzon</title>
    <link>https://mariamonzon.com/tag/machine-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mariamonzon.com/tag/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Machine Learning</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mariamonzon.com/media/icon_huaad826f52d8c51d03abf0418cbb027d5_448596_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://mariamonzon.com/tag/machine-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning based reach-and-grasp EEG decoder</title>
      <link>https://mariamonzon.com/project/eeg-grasp-decoder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mariamonzon.com/project/eeg-grasp-decoder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The most common technique to measure the brain noninvasively is the electroencephalogram (EEG), due to its ease of use and cost/performance trade-off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An EEG is a non-invasive technique that consists of placing electrodes on the head to monitor the electrical activity produced when neurons fire. The EEG records and measures electrical signals of the human brain from multiple cortical areas. Therefore, EEG monitoring allows us to quantify different types of brain waves, also known as neural oscillations. Some of the best-known and most-advertised applications of EEG-based neurotechnologies are brain-control of different types of devices&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the high number of degrees of freedom of the human hand, most actions of daily life can be executed incorporating only palmar, pincer and lateral grasp. In this study we attempt to discriminate these three different executed reach-and-grasp actions utilizing their EEG neural correlates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a cue-guided experiment (see Figure 1), 15 healthy individuals were asked to perform reach-and-grasp actions using daily life objects. We recorded
72 trials for each reach-and-grasp condition and from a no-movement condition. In an oﬄine multiclass classiﬁcation scenario (10 x 5 crossvalidation),
which incorporated not only all reach-and-grasp actions but also the no-movement condition, we used a window of 1000 ms for extracting time domain
features.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fully automatic extraction of mitral valve annulus motion parameters on long axis CINE CMR using deep learning</title>
      <link>https://mariamonzon.com/project/cardiac-parameter-extraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mariamonzon.com/project/cardiac-parameter-extraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Diastolic dysfunction is an important cause of cardiac insuf-
ficiency, defined as a malfunctioning filling of the heart during diastole.
The analysis of mitral valve motion is known to be relevant in the diagno-
sis of cardiac dysfunction. Cardiac motion parameters can be extracted
from Cardiac Magnetic Resonance (CMR) images. However, in clinical
setting valve motion modeling usually needs a manual intervention to lo-
calize the valvular plane. We propose two chained Convolutional Neural
Networks (CNN) for automatic tracking of mitral valve-annulus land-
marks on time-resolved 2-chamber and 4-chamber CMR images. 
The first CNN is trained to detect the region of interest and the second to
track the landmarks along the cardiac cycle. The presented deep learn-
ing system has high accuracy in terms of temporal landmark tracking
and motion assessment. Furthermore, we successfully extracted several
motion-related parameters thereby overcoming time-consuming annota-
tion and allowing statistical analysis over a large number of datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Frame Rate for Egocentric Video</title>
      <link>https://mariamonzon.com/project/adaptive-frame-sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mariamonzon.com/project/adaptive-frame-sampling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of the project seminar is to implement an adaptive sampling strategy to dynamically
tune the sampling rate of a wearable egocentric camera. The sampling rate will be tuned
based on context measure, i.e., a measure of motion, extracted from the frames.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increasing development new media and data acquisition techniques have lead to new
innovative video recording set ups. A clear example of that is the egocentric video, where
a camera on head or on the chest approximates the visual field of the camera wearer.
This new camera setting offers a valuable perspective to understand user&amp;rsquo;s activities and
their context. In this case, the wearable head-mounted egocentric camera set up pursued
a dietary event spotting in a free living condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A main feature of free-living data is a long recording duration. However, this kind of
camera often acquire irrelevant data for the analysis task.
In this work we introduce an adaptive sampling strategy to dynamically tune the sam-
pling rate of a wearable egocentric camera. The adaptive sampling rate is based on a
context measure. It is a motion measure, indicative if the recorded activity might be of
our interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the sampling strategy we implemented a computational simulation of resource consumption in terms of energy consumption and memory storage. For this purpose, I designed an analytical energy and memory model, a
nd base our analysis on data extracted from datasheets. Our energy and memory model considers
both sensing components, i.e., the cmos sensor, and processing, i.e., the microcontroller
to process the deep neural network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clear advantage of an adaptive frame rate is saving energy as the camera will not be
acquiring data continuously. 
Benefits from our method will be longer recording sessions, smaller battery employment or smaller
storage space usage. This would help to overcome the limitations of the video recording,
in terms of power consumption, while maintaining acceptable performance. 
Furthermore, less data acquisition will also mean an energy saving in processing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ECG-based algorithm for Annotation of Resuscitation Episode</title>
      <link>https://mariamonzon.com/project/ecg-annotation-svm-classifier/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mariamonzon.com/project/ecg-annotation-svm-classifier/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Out-of hospital cardiac arrest (OHCA) is one of the major causes of death in developed countries. Resuscitation guidelines recommend different treatments depending on the heart rhythm of the patient. The objective of this work is to develop a machine learning algorithm based on the ECG signal to automatically label heart rhythms in resuscitation episodes, a key tool for the retrospectively evaluation and improvement of the quality treatment. This work would help to systematise the annotation of databases since manual annotation of rhythms is a time-consuming task which can be an obstacle for handling large data sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The starting point of this project was a database composed of 1631 intervals of 3 seconds taken from a larger database containing OHCA 298 episodes. To review the ECG segments, a graphical interface (GUI) was developed which allows the display of the ECGs classified by the type of arrhythmia: 
asystole (AS), ventricular tachycardia (VT) that degenerates into ventricular fibrillation (VF), pulseless electrical activity (PEA) pulse generating rhythms (PR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://mariamonzon.com/images/egc-svm-annotation/GUI-visualization.png&#34; alt=&#34;GUI-example-visualization&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database has been processed using a machine learning algorithm and the results obtained using cross-validation. Two classifiers have been developed selecting five features of the ECG, first to identify AS, and then to discriminate organised rhythms (PR and PEA) from ventricular arrhythmias (VT and VF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://mariamonzon.com/images/egc-svm-annotation/ECG-classification-Example.png&#34; alt=&#34;ECG-Visualization&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These algorithms have been combined to create a three class rhythm classification algorithm. The total accuracy of the final algorithm was 90.9%. A precise algorithm was obtained for the classification of OHCA rhythm into: AS, organised,  and  shockable  rhythms.  This  algorithm  can  be  implemented  to  analyse resuscitation episodes using 3 seconds ECG segments, and could be integrated into new methods for retrospective analysis of OHCA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://mariamonzon.com/images/egc-svm-annotation/SVM-classification-results.png&#34; alt=&#34;ECG-Visualization&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results show that it is possible to automatically  interpret  resuscitation  cardiac  rhythm. These types of algorithms can be very useful since they allow an efficient rhythm classification with a minimum level of expert clinician supervision&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
